What do you want to eat today?
今天想吃什么？
-What do you want? -Curry rice!
-想吃什么？ -咖喱饭
Why did your family members pass away?
你的家人怎么会过世？
I...
我…
killed them.
杀了他们
Dear me...
天啊
Akari said that?
灯子这么说吗？
That's not true, is it?
这不是真的吧？
We kept asking her after that,
我们继续问下去
but she wouldn't tell us anything.
她却什么也不说
Well... I'm sorry,
不好意思
but I can't tell you guys anything today.
但我不能跟你们说
Because of that, remember?
你记得原因吧？
Please tell us! You're the only one we can rely on, President.
拜托告诉我们 我们只能靠你了 所长
Dear me, could you not use your charms on me?
拜托别这样诱惑我了
Then you can answer yes or no questions, right?
你可以回答对或不对吧？
What?
什么？
What's these? Oh, my!
这是什么？天啊
It's just like a quiz show! This is interesting!
好像益智节目 真有趣
-Then question one. -Okay.
-第一题 -好
Mita's deceased family members
三田小姐过世的家人
are her husband and child, right?
是她的先生和小孩吧？
Yes, that's right!
没错
Hey, how could you? That's why I didn't want to say anything.
干吗啦？所以我才什么都不想说
Just what's wrong?
是怎么回事？
Oh, there's 20 seconds left.
只剩20秒了
-15, 14... -Is Mita coming?
-15、14… -三田小姐要来吗？
That's right!
没错
-Come on, hide! -Hurry up!
-快躲起来 -快点
Ten, nine, eight, seven...
十、九、八、七
six, five, four, three, two, one.
六、五、四、三、二、一
Oh my, Akari.
灯子
You're right on time, as always.
每次都这么准时
What is it? You told me that there's something you want to tell me.
怎么了？你说有事要跟我说
I'm sorry, but...
不好意思
Could you please not reveal anything about my past from now on?
能不能请你不要再跟结和孩子们
To Yui and the children.
透露我的过去？
Got it. I'm sorry.
好的 抱歉
Since all of you are here, let me make myself clear.
既然大家都在 我就把话说清楚
From now on,
从今以后
I do not intend on answering any questions you may have.
我不会再回答你们的问题
Please excuse me.
先告辞了
Just tell us, please!
拜托跟我们说
She's right! Of course we'd get curious if you said something like that!
对啊 你这样说 我们反而更好奇
I searched on the internet,
我在网上查过
but I didn't see you listed as a suspect in any murder cases.
但没看到你被列为谋杀嫌疑犯
If you insist on questioning me, I will relieve myself of my duties.
你们执意问下去 我只能离职
Hey. What does it mean to "relieve myself of my duties"?
“离职”是什么意思？
Mita means that she's going to quit.
意思是三田小姐会离开
What? No!
什么？不行
I have an important request for you, Mita!
我有重要的事要你办 三田小姐
Fine.
好啦
Let's go, everyone.
大家走吧
Akari.
灯子
Could you be perhaps...
你会不会…
still concerned about what your husband's parents told you?
还在意你公婆说的话？
Didn't I tell you? That wasn't your fault.
我说过啦 不是你的错
Please excuse me.
先告辞了
-Thank you for the food.
-我开动了
Do you need anything from me?
还有什么事吗？
Oh, sorry.
不好意思
Right. Kii, didn't you say you have a request for Mita?
希衣 你不是有事 要拜托三田小姐吗？
I'm going to be acting as Dorothy from The Wizard of Oz
我在戏剧演出里
for our upcoming play performance.
要演《绿野仙踪》的桃乐茜
Mita, will you sew me a dress?
三田小姐 你能帮我做套洋装吗？
As you wish.
我知道了
Wow! You're great, Kii. It's the leading role!
希衣 你真厉害 这是主角
I see. It's on this coming Saturday. We have to attend it together.
是这周六演 我们要一起去看
What's wrong, Kii?
希衣 怎么了？
Daddy...
爸比…
You guys think he'll come?
你们觉得他会来吗？
What?
什么？
Yui, you think Dad's okay?
姐 爸还好吗？
He'll do what you asked, right?
他会照你说的做吧？
Prove that you love us, more than anyone else in this world.
证明你爱我们胜过世界上任何人
I want you to put your stone into the box.
我希望爸爸把石头放进这个盒子里
I'm sure he'll be fine.
他一定可以的
But...
不过…
Doesn't he still love that mistress?
他还爱着那小三吧？
He even tried to abandon us to marry her.
他甚至想抛下我们去娶她
Hey, Yui. Should we really just do nothing and wait?
姐 我们真的要这样干等吗？
That is...
那是…
something all of you should decide for yourselves.
你们要自己决定的事
There you go, pushing the question back to us again.
又把问题推还给我们了
Then could you pass a message to Dad?
那能请你传话给爸吗？
"You must attend Kii's play,
“你一定要参加希衣的表演
and let us hear your reply to my question."
还要回答我的问题”
As you wish.
我知道了
You surprised me...
我很意外
with that phone call telling me to save you.
会接到你向我求救的电话
Sorry.
抱歉
Come in.
请进
Want some coffee?
要喝咖啡吗？
It was as you said, Chief.
课长 你说对了
What?
什么？
Natori...
名取
He decided to have a blind date with the director's daughter.
他决定和董事的女儿相亲
I must be a fool.
我真的是傻了
I should have realized it earlier.
早该料到的
Natori told me just now.
名取刚刚问我
"Just how long do you plan on staying in this company?
“你还打算在这公司待多久？
Everyone wants you to quit. Why won't you realize it?"
难道不知道大家都想要你辞职吗？”
Sorry.
抱歉
It's all my fault.
都是我的错
Then...
那么…
Could you take responsibility?
能请你负责吗？
I only have you left, Keiichi.
我只剩你了 惠一
Why don't we go somewhere far away
我们干脆搬到异地
and start all over again?
重新开始吧？
Well...
这…
I'm joking. You can't just abandon your kids.
我开玩笑的 你不能丢下孩子
I'm returning to the countryside to have a blind date.
我会回到乡下相亲
Wait, Mie. Hold on!
美枝 等等
You surprised me!
吓死我了
If I remember, you're...
我没记错的话 你是…
I'm Mita, a housekeeper.
我是家政妇三田
What's wrong, Mita?
怎么了 三田小姐？
I have a message for you from Yui.
结要我传话给你
Please excuse me.
我先走了
I always had to work during the weekends,
我周末都要工作
so I've never attended her school events.
所以没参加过她学校的活动
So?
所以呢？
What?
什么？
What should I tell Yui and the children?
我该跟结和孩子们说什么？
Oh, well...
这个…
For now, please don't tell them about that lady just now.
先别跟他们提到刚才的小姐
Besides, we weren't doing anything indecent.
我们没做什么见不得人的事
Understood.
我知道了
Also, about the play...
演出的事
Of course I'd love to go,
我当然很想去
but I still don't know what I should do, to be honest.
但老实说 我还是不知道该怎么办
What should I do to prove my love for them as a father?
我该怎么证明我是爱他们的父亲？
Even if I said I love them,
就算我说我爱他们
I don't think they would believe it.
他们也不会相信
What do you think I should do, Mita?
你觉得我该怎么做 三田小姐？
That is...
那是…
"Something you should decide for yourself."
“你要自己决定的事”
Please don't say that. Help me.
拜托别这样说 帮帮我
If I mess up this time, it's all over for me.
我这次搞砸就完蛋了
I still have work to do, so please excuse me.
我还有工作要做 先告辞了
Wait a minute. Hey, Mita! Wait!
等一下 三田小姐
It hurts!
好痛
I'm sorry...
不好意思
but could you not stand behind me?
但能请你别站在我身后吗？
So, what did Dad say?
爸怎么说？
"I will definitely attend the play,
“我一定会去看表演
and prove my love for the kids. So don't worry."
向孩子证明我的爱 别担心”
That was what he said.
他这么说
He sounds really confident, but will it be fine?
他感觉很有信心 但真的没问题吗？
Didn't Dad probably tell you to say that for now?
爸该不会要你先这样讲吧？
Yes.
对
What's up with that?
搞什么啊？
Hey. Did it look like he's not meeting his mistress already?
他看起来是不是没跟小三见面了？
It's done.
做好了
Wow! It looks like those being sold in shops!
好厉害 好像买来的
This is awesome!
好厉害
Mita avoided our question for the first time, didn't she?
这是三田小姐第一次 回避我们的问题 对吧？
They couldn't still be having rendezvous, right?
他们不会还在约会吧？
What's a "rendezvous"?
什么是“约会”？
That means, a man and woman going to a hotel--
就是男人和女人去旅馆…
Don't teach her weird things.
别乱教她
Kii, why don't you try on the dress?
希衣 你试穿看看洋装吧？
Okay! Then will you guys practice with me?
好 你们能陪我练习吗？
What? Give me a break!
什么？不要吧
Please! Daddy's going to watch it, so I don't want to make a mistake.
拜托 爸比会去看 我不想出错
Okay. I'll be Dorothy, Yui will be the Scarecrow,
我当桃乐茜 姐当稻草人
Kakeru will be the Tin Woodman and Kai will be the Lion.
小翔当锡人 小斗当狮子
Then who will be the Wicked Witch?
那谁当坏女巫？
Is that an order?
这是命令吗？
We came here to punish you, Wicked Witch!
我们要来处罚你 坏女巫
I wanted to make all of you my slaves,
我原本想拿你们来当奴隶
but there's no way a tin man, scarecrow, lion and a small girl like you
但锡人、稻草人、狮子和小女孩
will be useful, so I will tear all of you apart.
根本派不上用场 所以我会杀光你们
You're scary, Mita!
三田小姐 你好可怕
Actually, could you put in more emotion?
你能多加点感情吗？
I'm sorry.
抱歉
Then let's try again.
再来一次吧
We came here to punish you, Wicked Witch!
我们要来处罚你 坏女巫
I wanted to make all of you my slaves,
我原本想拿你们来当奴隶
but there's no way a tin man, scarecrow, lion and a small girl like you
但锡人、稻草人、狮子和小女孩
will be useful, so I will tear all of you apart.
根本派不上用场 所以我会杀光你们
Hey, it's your line next, Yui!
姐 接下来是你的台词
Sorry, one minute.
抱歉 等一下
What? Your boyfriend again?
什么？又是男朋友吗？
TAKUYA OZAWA I'M SORRY ABOUT THE OTHER DAY
（小泽拓也：前几天很抱歉）
"PLEASE, LET'S HAVE A PROPER TALK."
（拜托跟我好好谈谈）
I'm sorry about the other day.
前几天的事很抱歉
You told me to elope with you,
你要我跟你私奔
but I didn't think you'd do it for real.
但我没想到你是认真的
-What I mean is-- -I'm sorry.
-我意思是… -对不起
I want to break up with you, Ozawa.
学长 我要跟你分手
I realized something.
我发现
When I was going out with you,
我跟你交往
I was just trying to ignore my selfish side as well as the reality.
只是因为我自私 想逃离现实
I don't want to run away anymore.
我不想再逃了
I want to become stronger.
我想变得更坚强
Please excuse me.
我先走了
Urara!
小丽
What is it?
怎么了？
Thanks for what you did the other day.
前几天的事很谢谢你
What?
什么？
Let's go home, Yui.
回家吧 小结
Oh, I...
那…
That's... Don't mention it!
那没什么啦
That's with your strange reaction?
你这什么奇怪的反应？
Well...
但是…
This is the first time.
这是你第一次
You actually thanked me.
感谢我
Could you apologize to Grandpa on my behalf, too?
能请你也替我向外公道歉吗？
Everyone you care about dies!
你亲近的人都会死掉！
Don't worry. He should get chastised once in a while.
没关系 偶尔也该有人骂骂他
Besides, Dad's worried about the slap he gave you.
而且爸打了你之后很内疚
I'm totally fine. It was all my fault.
没事的 都是我的错
What is it?
怎么了？
It feels like you've matured
你好像长大了
and become more reliable.
更可靠了
That's not true. What are you saying?
才没有 胡说什么啊？
I can't lose to you. All right, I'm getting pumped up now!
我不能输给你 我要加油
-Sorry! -Hey, are you all right?
-抱歉 -你还好吗？
I'm totally fine.
一点事也没有
I'm home.
我回来了
What are you up to, Dad?
爸 你在干吗？
Do I smell?
我很臭吗？
What? What are you saying all of a sudden?
怎么突然这样问？
I just remember Yui and the kids saying that to me in the past.
我记得小结和孩子们这样说过
"You smell, Grandpa!"
“外公 你好臭”
That's not true.
才没有
Yui also wants to apologize for the mean remarks the other day.
小结想为前几天说的话道歉
Come on. I'll do this, so why don't you go in the bath now?
我来晾吧 你去泡个澡吧？
Okay.
好
You know...
那个…
I'm actually quite happy living with you, Dad.
我跟你住得很开心 爸
Shut up.
闭嘴
Right. Kii's playing the main lead in her upcoming play performance.
希衣在戏剧演出担任主角
I told her that you'll go watch.
我说了你会去看
She probably doesn't want me there.
她说不定不想要我去
Why don't you be honest?
你为什么不诚实点呢？
Yui's being considerate of you.
希衣已经给你台阶下了
Since when did I ask her to be considerate?
我有叫她给吗？
You know that's not what I mean.
我不是那个意思
I will never go!
我绝对不会去
Don't you go, too!
你也别去
HOW TO BECOME A GOOD FATHER
（《怎么当个好父亲》）
MIE KAZAMA: I'M RETURNING TO THE COUNTRYSIDE THIS SUNDAY.
（风间美枝：我周日会回乡下）
THANK YOU FOR EVERYTHING.
（谢谢你的照顾）
I heard about it.
我听说了
Congratulations on your engagement, Natori.
恭喜你订婚了 名取
You're jumping the gun.
你这话说得太早了
Honestly, I was interested in you, Natori.
老实说我原本对你有兴趣的 名取
There's no way we'll win the director's daughter.
但我们是赢不过董事的女儿
We'll count on you forever in work!
以后工作都要靠你了
Just leave everything to me.
包在我身上
I believe I told you not to make Kazama unhappy.
我说过了别让风间不开心
Don't make such a scary face.
表情不用这么恐怖吧
Hold on.
等等
Just give it a rest already.
你够了吧？
Unlike you, I'm someone important in this company.
我可不像你 我对公司很重要
Don't mess with me!
嘴巴放干净点
Our affair was exposed, and you told her you loved her.
我们偷情的事曝光后 你跟她说你爱她
And you'll abandon her this easily just for your own career?
现在却为了前途随便抛下她？
Just what is love? Hey, tell me!
这算什么爱？告诉我啊
What are you saying?
你在说什么啊？
Let go!
放手
I just don't get it!
我实在搞不懂
What should I do to prove that I really love someone?
该怎么做才能证明我爱他们？
Do you just need to tell them that you love them?
只要跟对方说你爱他们就可以了吗？
Hey, tell me! What should I do?
说啊 我该怎么做？
I don't know what to do anymore!
我不知道该怎么办了
I really don't know!
我真的不知道
Goodbye, Scarecrow, Tin Woodman and Lion.
再见 稻草人、锡人和狮子
Thank you for everything.
谢谢你们
Don't go, Dorothy!
桃乐茜 别走
Hey. It's your line now, Kakeru.
翔 轮到你了
What? Oh, sorry!
什么？对不起
Come on, do it properly!
拜托认真一点
Sorry.
抱歉
I will get the door.
我去开门
By the way, I have exams.
话说我还有考试
I don't have time for this.
我没时间陪练了
It's for our cute little sister. Come on, one more time.
这是为了我们可爱的妹妹 再一次吧
Don't go, Dorothy.
桃乐茜 别走
Hey, I heard you guys were practicing,
我听说你们在练习
so let me do something, too! I can be the mean stepmother.
也让我加入吧 我能当坏后母
Don't worry, Urara.
没关系 小丽
There's no mean stepmother in this story, too.
而且故事里也没有坏后母
I see.
好吧
Right, I bought some food, so let's share them!
我带了食物 一起吃吧
They sell delicious takoyaki!
这家章鱼烧超好吃
Look, Urara! Mita made this dress for me!
小丽你看 三田小姐 做了这件洋装给我
What?
什么？
Oh, sorry!
对不起
It's only going to get dirtier if you rub the stains!
你越擦只会越脏
The play's tomorrow!
明天就要演出了
All because someone butted in again!
又是因为有人爱管闲事
Please! Just don't do anything and stand still!
什么也别做 站着就好
Sorry.
对不起
Stop that! Urara didn't do that on purpose.
好了啦 小丽不是故意的
Mita, could you do something about this before tomorrow?
三田小姐 你在明天前能清干净吗？
Don't worry.
没问题
Kii, Mita's going to remove the stain for you, so let's have some takoyaki.
希衣 三田小姐会帮你把 洋装洗干净 来吃章鱼烧吧
Okay.
好
Here you go! I'll go get some tea now.
请慢用 我去泡茶
-Yui. -Yes?
-姐姐 -嗯？
Daddy will come tomorrow, right?
爸比明天会来吧？
What?
什么？
Well, yes.
会啦
I think so.
应该吧
Don't worry! You should believe in your dad!
别担心 你们要对爸爸有信心
Mita. Has Dad contacted you?
三田小姐 爸跟你联络了吗？
No, he hasn't.
没有
Then shall I call him?
我该打给他吗？
No! Don't do anything unnecessary.
不用多此一举
Sorry.
抱歉
This is Mita, the housekeeper.
我是家政妇三田
Mita.
三田小姐
Can I meet you after you're done with work today?
你今天下班可以跟我碰面吗？
I'll pay you the overtime fee.
我要付你加班费
As you wish.
我知道了
What do you need from me?
你需要什么？
Actually...
其实…
I've been fired from my company.
我被公司开除了
And I still don't know how I should prove my love for the kids.
我还是不知道 该怎么向孩子证明我的爱
This is the worst.
这真是糟透了
At this rate,
这样下去
I'll never have the confidence to put my stone into Kii's box.
我根本没信心 把石头放进希衣的盒子里
Huh?
奇怪
It's not here.
不见了
I lost the stone Kii gave me!
我把希衣给的石头弄丢了
Wait a minute...
等等…
Mita, do you have a torchlight?
三田小姐 你有手电筒吗？
I do.
有
Seriously, when did I drop it?
我到底什么时候掉的？
Oh, there it is!
找到了
What with all these similar stones?
怎么都长这么像？
Just where did I drop it?
我掉在哪里？
Just what in the world should I do?
我到底该怎么办？
Mita.
三田小姐
You'll do everything I ask, right?
我说什么你都会做吧？
If it is within my means.
只要我办得到就行
Then could you let me return to the company?
你能让我回到公司吗？
I can't.
没办法
Could you turn back time?
你能让时间倒转吗？
I guessed as much. Then...
我想也是 那…
Right.
对了
Could you stop the play performance tomorrow?
你能让明天的表演延期吗？
If the play's postponed,
如果表演延期
I might come up with an idea to earn the kids' forgiveness.
我也许能想到办法争取孩子原谅
Right! Please do that!
没错 就请你这样做吧
As you wish.
我知道了
THE WIZARD OF OZ
（《绿野仙踪》）
Stop that!
不行这样
Why did you hit me?
干吗打我？
I'm actually a coward.
我其实很胆小
I can't sleep because I'm afraid of the dark.
我不敢睡觉 因为我怕黑
Will Oz be able to grant me courage?
奥兹能给我勇气吗？
-Dad's still not here yet? -I'm sure he will!
-爸还没来吗？ -他一定可以
-I'm sure he'll be here soon. -That's right! Why don't you...
-他一定马上就来了 -没错 你…
Please stop this!
不要这样
-Mita? -Mita!
-三田小姐？ -三田小姐
Mita!
三田小姐
Hey! Someone call the police!
谁快报警！
Stop, Mita!
不要这样 三田小姐！
Hey! What are you doing?
你在干吗？
THE WIZARD OF OZ
（《绿野仙踪》）
Stop it!
住手
NOVEMBER 26TH, 10 A.M. TO 2 P.M. MISAWA KINDERGARTEN
（11月26日早上10点到下午2点 三泽幼儿园）
This is Mita, the housekeeper.
我是家政妇三田
Oh, hello? It's me.
喂？是我
Well, about the matter at the kindergarten I asked yesterday...
我昨天请你处理幼儿园的事
Could you forget about that?
能请你忽略吗？
I'm sorry.
抱歉
It's too late.
已经太迟了
What?
什么？
Just what did you do?
你做了什么？
Wait, where are you right now?
等等 你现在在哪？
I cannot answer you.
我不能回答
Hey, Mita!
等等 三田小姐
Just what will happen to the play?
演出要怎么办？
Tsubasa was really looking forward to it!
小翼可是很期待
I'm sorry, but the police will need to do their investigation first.
不好意思 警察要先调查
Excuse me. What happened here?
不好意思 是怎么回事？
We received a warning call.
我们接到恐吓电话
If we don't cancel the play,
如果不取消演出
the kindergarten will be bombed.
就要引爆幼儿园
What?
什么？
Don't tell me...
不会吧？
Your housekeeper isn't behind this, is she?
不会是你的家政妇搞的鬼吧？
I'm really sorry about this!
我真的很抱歉
ASAZU POLICE STATION
（浅津警察局）
I'm glad we settled matters with the kindergarten amicably.
幸好跟幼儿园和解了
But to be honest, this is a serious crime.
但这可是重罪
They gave me a harsh reprimand.
他们狠狠斥责了我一顿
Excuse me, but what about the play?
话说演出怎样了？
It has ended.
结束了
I see.
这样啊
THEATER PLAY THE WIZARD OF OZ
（戏剧演出《绿野仙踪》）
I wished I could have seen...
真希望能看到…
Kii's acting in The Wizard of Oz.
希衣的《绿野仙踪》演出
You must think I'm being ridiculous.
你一定觉得我很可笑
I'm such a hopeless man.
我真是无药可救
I should have died instead of my wife.
死的应该是我 不是我太太
Damn it!
可恶！
Daddy!
爸比
-Dad! -Daddy!
-爸 -爸比
Daddy!
爸比
Why are they here?
他们怎么在这？
Yui and the kids asked me
结和孩子们问我
why you tried to stop the play.
你为什么要阻止演出
So I told them that you lost your job as well as the stone Kii gave,
所以我说你失业 还把希衣的石头弄丢了
and that you no longer have
你不再有自信
the confidence to prove your love for them.
能证明你爱他们
I told them everything.
我全跟他们说了
-Daddy! -Dad!
-爸比 -爸
-Don't come over!
-别过来
You heard from Mita, right?
你们听到三田小姐的话了吧？
I don't have the right to be your father!
我没资格当你们父亲
You guys are better off being adopted by your grandfather!
你们给外公收养比较好！
I'm sure you'll be happier that way!
你们这样一定会比较幸福！
We get it already!
知道了
Daddy!
爸比
Watch me act as Dorothy!
看我演桃乐茜吧
In fact,
其实
you must watch it!
你非看不可
The old hag next door complained,
讨人厌的邻居抱怨
and Kii was removed from her role!
害得希衣被换角
What?
什么？
Dad!
爸
Our own play performance hasn't ended yet.
我们自己的演出还没结束
Goodbye, Scarecrow, Tin Woodman and Lion.
再见 稻草人、锡人和狮子
Thank you for everything.
谢谢你们
I will never forget all of you!
我绝不会忘记你们
Don't leave, Dorothy!
桃乐茜 别走
If we hadn't met you,
我们要是没遇到你
I wouldn't have received this gentle heart!
我就不会有温柔的心
this wonderful brain!
我也不会有聪明的头脑
And I would have remained as a coward.
我也还会是个胆小鬼
I'm sorry.
对不起
But I have to go home.
但我要回家了
I have to go home, where my beloved family is waiting for me.
我要回家 我亲爱的家人在等我
All right! Everyone, come sing with me!
好 大家跟我一起唱
After climbing up this slope
爬上这座山丘之后
There's a tree to the right
往右边走有一棵树
When you turn at the tree and walk straight
在树的地方转弯 然后继续前进
Your beloved home is there waiting for you
你可爱的家在等着你
What's wrong, Dad?
怎么了 爸爸？
Well...
只是…
I wish your mother could have seen this.
真希望你们的妈妈也能看到
I'm sure that...
你们的妈妈…
your mom would have loved to see this, more than anyone else.
一定会看得比谁都开心
But...
可是…
It's all because of me.
都是因为我
Your mother...
你们的妈妈…
Unlike me, she was full of love.
跟我不一样 她充满爱心
Ever since I met her for the first time,
从我一认识她
she always cried, got angry, and laughed.
她就时常大哭大笑 也会发脾气
She was always honest to her feelings.
她从来不掩饰自己的感受
She hated to keep secrets and worried too much,
她讨厌秘密 也很爱操心
but she loved me more than anyone else.
但她比谁都还爱我
Did you guys know
你们知道
what she told me when we got married?
我们结婚时 她说了什么吗？
"Thank you for granting me my dream."
“谢谢你实现了我的梦想”
That was how she is.
她性格就是这么好
I should have loved her more.
我应该多爱她一点的
I...
我…
I let your beloved mother die!
我害你们心爱的妈妈死了
It's not something that can be easily forgiven.
不管我道歉几次 都不能轻易被原谅
But I'm really sorry!
但我真的很抱歉
I'm really, really sorry!
我真的真的很抱歉
You don't have to forgive me.
你们不用原谅我
You don't have to love me.
你们不用爱我
But I...
但是我…
I...
我…
I want to love all of you!
我想爱你们每一个人
I want to continue loving all of you for the rest of my life!
我这辈子想好好爱你们大家
Unlike other fathers...
我和其他父亲不同
I can't say that I love you confidently.
我没办法很有自信地说出我爱你们
But that's what I feel now. I'm not lying.
但这就是我的感受 我没在说谎
I want to love all of you, as much as possible!
我想用尽全力爱你们
I want us to be together forever!
我希望我们永远在一起
I want to see you kids grow up, and watch how you lead your lives!
我想看你们长大 参与你们的人生
I want to talk about a lot of things with you!
我想跟你们聊好多事
I want to tell you guys about your mother!
我想跟你们说妈妈的事
When you're having a tough time,
你们如果遇上困难
I will support you.
我会支持你们
I'll do anything I can!
我会尽我所能
I'll do everything I can to protect you!
我会尽全力保护你们
So...
所以…
So, I...
所以我…
Could you let me be your father?
能让我当你们的父亲吗？
I lost Kii's stone,
我把希衣的石头弄丢了
but let me be your father!
但请让我当你们的父亲
I beg you!
求求你们
I'm sorry, but I acted out of my place.
抱歉 但我自作主张了
What?
什么？
Mita...
三田小姐
How did you find this?
你在哪找到的？
I thought that you might have lost it in your company,
我想你可能是在公司弄丢的
so I searched the trash cans there.
就去找了那里的垃圾桶
Then...
所以…
You've been searching since last night?
你从昨晚就开始找？
Don't worry. I will not charge you any overtime fees.
别担心 我不会收你加班费
Thank you so much!
谢谢你
Daddy.
爸比
Daddy's finally back.
爸比终于回来了
Mommy!
妈咪
Stop crying, Dad. You're a man!
别哭了 爸 你可是个男人
Okay.
好
I'm sorry.
对不起
Right, Yui. Can we take a photo to remember this day?
姐姐 我们能拍照留念吗？
Sounds good. Today's the day our dad revived.
好啊 今天是爸爸重生的日子
What does that even mean?
这是什么意思？
Not yet, Yui?
姐 还没好吗？
One moment. I need to set the timer.
等一下 我要设定计时器
Join us, Mita.
跟我们一起拍吧 三田小姐
I'm fine.
不用了
Don't say that.
别这样说嘛
You're just like family to us, Mita.
三田小姐 你就像我们的家人一样
I'm sorry...
抱歉
but I'm not your family.
但我不是你们的家人
Okay, I'll take one first. Say cheese!
好 我先拍一张吧 笑一个
All right!
好
-Hurry up! -Okay.
-快点 -好
Sorry, everyone!
大家抱歉
My student got into some trouble right at this time and...
我学生刚好挑这时间出了事
-Urara, move! -How did the play go?
-小丽 走开 -演出还好吗？
We're taking a photo! Hey!
我们在拍照 喂
The 7:15 a.m. express bus heading to Haneda Airport will be departing soon.
早上7点15分往羽田机场的 高速巴士要发车了
We ask that all passengers board the bus immediately.
请所有乘客赶快上车
The 7:15 a.m. express bus heading to Haneda Airport will be departing soon.
早上7点15分往羽田机场的 高速巴士要发车了
We ask that all passengers board the bus immediately.
请所有乘客赶快上车
Kazama!
风间
Keiichi...
惠一
I...
我…
I still love you now.
还是爱着你
What?
什么？
I want to marry you.
我想跟你结婚
Are you serious?
你是认真的吗？
If you would become the children's mother.
但你要愿意当我孩子的母亲
My kids kept calling me "Dad" over and over yesterday,
我的小孩昨天一直叫我“爸爸”
and I finally realized something.
我终于意识到一件事
It's such a wonderful feeling to be called "Father."
能被叫“父亲”是件美好的事
I was a fool for not realizing it the entire time.
我一直以来都没意识到 真是个傻子
Just as my name implies, I've always been the happiest man in the world.
我的名字代表着 我该是世上最有恩惠的人
We are departing soon. Please board the bus.
我们要发车了 请上车
Regarding the adoption of the kids...
关于收养孩子的事
I would like to officially reject it.
我要郑重拒绝
I'm truly sorry.
我真的很抱歉
From now on, I will work hard so that
从今以后 我会尽力
you and the children will acknowledge me as their father.
让你和孩子们承认我是他们的父亲
I...
我…
I may be a small boat,
我虽然是艘小船
but no matter what storm approaches,
但不管风浪再大
no matter which enemy attacks us,
不管是什么敌人攻过来
I will protect the kids
我都会保护孩子
and take them to each of their destinations.
带他们每个人到达目的地
I'm really sorry.
我真的很抱歉
I'm sorry, Grandpa.
外公 对不起
I said mean things to you the other day.
我上次说了难听的话
It's not that we dislike you.
我们不是讨厌你
We just decided to be with Dad.
只是决定要和爸一起生活
We don't want to be apart any more.
我们不想再分开了
Please forgive us.
请原谅我们
Come on, Dad! Why don't you say something?
好了啦 爸 你说点话吧？
Do whatever you want.
随便你们
What?
什么？
I don't care about you guys any longer.
我不在乎你们了
I don't even think of you as grandchildren.
我根本不把你们当孙子看了
Wait, Dad? Dad!
等一下 爸？
Sorry! Dad.
抱歉 爸
How was Grandpa?
外公怎么样？
He was mad. He told us to do whatever we want.
他很生气 说随便我们
I knew it.
我就知道
Can't be helped. It's all my fault.
没办法 都是我的错
I'll do my best to make him forgive me.
我会尽力让他原谅我
Okay? All right. I'm leaving now.
好 我出门了
What? Where are you going?
你要去哪里？
Right. It's a weekend.
对啊 现在是周末
I have to find a job quickly, and make Grandpa acknowledge me.
我要尽快找到工作 让外公看得起我
You should get changed.
你该换衣服
Oh, I'm fine like this.
我这样没关系
You must have sweated profusely
你一定流了很多汗
since you were nervous from meeting your father-in-law.
因为你见岳父很紧张
What?
什么？
Okay.
好
-What's wrong, Dad? -What?
-怎么了 爸？ -什么？
No, it's just that the shirt's just been ironed,
没事 只是这件衬衫刚烫过
so it feels really good to wear.
所以穿起来很舒服
Mita.
三田小姐
Thank you.
谢谢你
That is...
你这句话
something you should tell your late wife.
该说给你过世的太太听
I am only imitating what your wife did.
我只是学了你太太做过的事
Thanks, Nagiko.
谢谢你 凪子
I'm sorry that
对不起
I've never thanked you when you were alive.
你还活着时 我从没谢过你
ASUDA RESIDENCE
（阿须田家）
KEIICHI, NAGIKO, YUI, KAKERU, KAITO, KII
（惠一、凪子、结 翔、海斗、希衣）
Well then, I'm leaving.
好 我出门了
-Have a safe trip.
-路上小心
Have a safe trip.
路上小心
Mita.
三田小姐
We want you to go somewhere with us.
我们希望你跟我们去个地方
Mita. We thought about this,
三田小姐 我们想过了
but you always come here because it's a memorable place
但你常来这里 是因为这里对你和你家人
for you and your family, right?
很有纪念意义 对吧？
You always ordered this and ate it together, right?
你们每次都会点 这套餐一起吃 对吧？
You would never kill your family members, Mita.
三田小姐 你才不会杀死家人
I'm sure you just feel responsible for their deaths. Right?
你一定觉得要为他们的死负责吧？
Hey. Tell us, Mita.
告诉我们 三田小姐
I will protect you!
我会保护你
I need to prepare for dinner.
我该准备晚餐了
Hey! Wait! Just wait a minute!
喂 等一下
I believe I have said this before.
我相信我之前说过了
If you insist on questioning me, I will relieve myself of my duties.
如果你们执意追问 我就会辞职
You killed them!
你杀了他们
Give me back my son and grandchild!
把我的儿子和孙子还来
Enough with the apologies!
不用再道歉了
Don't you ever dare smile again...
你到死前…
until you die!
都不准再笑
MITA FINALLY COMES CLEAN ABOUT HER PAST
（三田终于要说出她的过往）
I tried to smile as much as I could.
我努力露出笑容
He started to stalk me.
他开始跟踪骚扰我
He cornered me, over and over.
他一再把我逼到死角
My husband and son died.
我丈夫和儿子死了
And with that...
就这样
My future disappeared from my life.
我的未来从人生中消失了
I'm Mita, the housekeeper.
我是家政妇三田
He chased me out of the house...
爸把我从家里赶出来了
I'm sorry!
抱歉
When I first received a monaka from Ms. Harumi,
我第一次拿到最中饼 是家政妇介绍所所长给我的
I smiled from the bottom of my heart.
发自内心露出笑容
My mother grew to hate me even more.
我母亲变得更恨我了
I kept begging for forgiveness, over and over.
我一再乞求原谅
"You don't have to do anything."
“你什么也不用做”
"Just don't smile until you die."
“到死前都不要笑就好了”
Subtitle translation by: Qianni Lu
字幕翻译：吴敬美